<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yikun-baio.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yikun-baio.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-26T18:59:09+00:00</updated><id>https://yikun-baio.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">recommanded mathmatical references</title><link href="https://yikun-baio.github.io/blog/2023/references/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="recommanded mathmatical references"/><published>2023-07-28T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-28T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://yikun-baio.github.io/blog/2023/references</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yikun-baio.github.io/blog/2023/references/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="probability-theory">Probability theory</h3> <ul> <li> <p><a href="https://services.math.duke.edu/~rtd/PTE/PTE5_011119.pdf"><strong>Probability theory and examples</strong></a> Renowned as the ‘Bible’ of probability theory, this book offers a comprehensive understanding of basic probability concepts, using measure theory language. It encompasses various fundamental concepts such as random variables, sample space, stochastic processes, martingales, expectation, the Law of Large Numbers, Central Limit Theorem, Gaussian processes, Markov processes, and more.</p> </li> <li> <p><a href="https://www.math.uci.edu/~rvershyn/papers/HDP-book/HDP-book.html"><strong>High dimensional probability theory</strong></a> This book is an invaluable asset in learning theory, particularly covering aspects like generative capability, sample complexity, statistical convergence rate, etc. It presents many elementary inequalities in probability theory, such as Markov inequality, Chebyshev’s Inequality, Gaussian Concentration Inequality, and concepts like Sub-Gaussian distribution, log-concave distribution.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="functional-analysis">Functional analysis</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://users.math.msu.edu/users/schenke6/920/920notes.pdf"><strong>Functional Analysis (Math 920) Lecture Notes</strong></a></li> <li><a href="https://bookstore.ams.org/gsm-143"><strong>Lecture Notes on Functional Analysis: With Applications to Linear Partial Differential Equation</strong></a> These lecture notes offer an easy-to-follow introduction to functional analysis. They cover foundational inequalities widely used in probability theory, measure concentration, and information theory, such as the Minkowski inequality. The notes also introduce key concepts in optimization, like dual space, the Riesz representation theorem, and weak topology (weak convergence and so on).</li> </ul> <h3 id="information-theory">Information theory</h3> <ul> <li> <p><a href="http://staff.ustc.edu.cn/~cgong821/Wiley.Interscience.Elements.of.Information.Theory.Jul.2006.eBook-DDU.pdf"><strong>Element of information theory</strong></a> This classic reference book in the field of information theory explains essential concepts like entropy, mutual information, KL-divergence, etc., and their interpretations in information theory. It’s a valuable resource for machine learning researchers.</p> </li> <li> <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1212.4663"><strong>Concentration of Measure Inequalities in Information Theory, Communications and Coding (Second Edition)</strong></a> An easily digestible monograph, it details basic measure concentration inequalities, optimal transportation inequalities, information inequalities and their relations, including famous inequalities such as Talagrand’s inequality, HWI inequalities, logarithmic Sobolev inequalities.</p> </li> </ul> <hr/> ]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reference"/><category term="math"/><category term="ML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[references]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">references for introduction of optimal transport</title><link href="https://yikun-baio.github.io/blog/2023/references_OT/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="references for introduction of optimal transport"/><published>2023-07-28T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2023-07-28T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://yikun-baio.github.io/blog/2023/references_OT</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yikun-baio.github.io/blog/2023/references_OT/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="basic-introduction">Basic introduction</h3> <ul> <li> <p><a href="https://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/research/cia/files/teaching/Optimal_Transport_Notes.pdf"><strong>Introduction to optimal transport</strong></a>. Penned by Dr. <a href="https://www.matthewthorpe.co.uk">Mathew Thorpe</a>, this lecture note is an accessible introduction to optimal transport theory. It covers fundamental concepts such as the Kantorovich theorem, the existence of the solution to the Optimal Transport problem, and the Boniner theorem. This material is highly suitable for beginners in this field.</p> </li> <li> <p><a href="https://ems.press/books/etb/190"><strong>An Invitation to Optimal Transport, Wasserstein Distances, and Gradient Flows</strong></a> This monograph by Dr. <a href="https://people.math.ethz.ch/~afigalli/">Alessio Figalli</a> delves into various significant and engaging concepts in Optimal Transport theory, including the Wasserstein geodesic, the Riemannian structure of the Wasserstein space, and the Wasserstein Gradient flow.</p> </li> </ul> <h3 id="transportation-inequality">Transportation inequality</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1212.4663"><strong>Concentration of Measure Inequalities in Information Theory, Communications and Coding (Second Edition)</strong></a> An easily digestible monograph, it details basic measure concentration inequalities, optimal transportation inequalities, information inequalities and their relations, including famous inequalities such as Talagrand’s inequality, HWI inequalities, logarithmic Sobolev inequalities.</li> </ul> <h3 id="computation-of-optimal-transport">Computation of optimal transport</h3> <ul> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.00567"><strong>Computational Optimal Transport</strong></a> A quintessential textbook on Optimal Transport computation, it presents various key algorithms for OT computation such as linear programming, the Sinkhorn algorithm, Barycenter, etc. It also provides an introduction to the basics of Gromov-Wasserstein distances.</li> </ul> <h3 id="monographs-in-ot-theory">Monographs in OT theory</h3> <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1009.3856"><strong>Introduction to Optimal Transport Theory</strong></a>, <a href="https://bookstore.ams.org/gsm-58"><strong>Topics in optimal transportation</strong></a>, <a href="https://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-3-540-71050-9"><strong>optimal transport: old and new</strong></a>, These three textbooks encompass most of the classical theoretical concepts in optimal transport theory such as the Kantorovich Duality theorem, Brenier theorem, weak-topology in Wasserstein space, transportation inequality, etc. It’s advisable to have some background in differential geometry and continuity equations before delving into the advanced content of these books. They offer an exciting exploration of various topics and open problems in classical Optimal Transport theory.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Reference"/><category term="OT"/><category term="ML"/><category term="math"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[reference]]></summary></entry></feed>